Miguel Xochicale

My research interests are in real-time and automatic signal and image processing techniques for AI-based fetal biomechanics.

Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging School of Biomedical Engineering and Imaging Sciences Department of Biomedical Engineering King's College London, UK

A http://mxochicale.github.io/ · in mxochicale

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Engineering at The University of Birmingham

Birmingham, UK

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019. Thesis: 🗗 GitHub: 🖶 Website: 🗹

M.Sc. in Signal Processing at Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE)

Puebla, México

Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers.

Sep 2004 - Sep 2006

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek Awarded MSc degree: 01/11/2006. Thesis: 🛭 GitHub: 🖶

Research Experience

Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging at King's College London, UK Sep 2021 – Present

- PIs: Dr Andrew King and Dr. Alberto Gomez
- · I am scientifically contributing to automatic biometric recognition of Electrocardiography ultrasound data using real-time deep learning techniques and frameworks with Python, CUDA, C++ and Qt programming languages via GitHub. See more at (27).

Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering at King's College London, UK Apr 2019 - Aug 2021

- PIs: Prof. Tom Vercauteren and Dr. Wenfeng Xia
- I pushed forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions where was involved in the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system (QMS) for clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. See more at ().

Supervision and Teaching Experience

020 -
02

- Supervision: Pablo Prieto Roca and Samuel Eyob. KURF projects on 3DGANs for US imaging. Jun 2022 - Aug 2022 Feb 2021 – Aug 2022 Supervision: Tsz Yan (Goosie) Leung, MSc in Medical Engineering and Physics. Project: Simple US guidance intervention.
- Supervision: Thea Bautista, M. Eng. in Biomedical Engineering. Project: DCGANs for fetal US imaging. Oct 2021 - May 2022
- Supervision: Guilherme Gomes de Figueiredo and Amal Hussein. KURF projects on DCGANs for US imaging. Jun 2021 – Aug 2021
- Supervision: Alexander Mitton, M.Sc. in Medical Engineering and Physics. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia. Jan 2020 - Sep 2020
- Jan 2022 Apr 2022 Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Alejandro Granados
- Jan 2021 Apr 2021 Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu
- Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles Jan 2020 - Apr 2020

The University of Birmingham

Jun 2018 - Dec 2018

Present

- Supervision: Dinghuang Zhang, M.Sc. in Computer Engineering. Project: Tools for human-humanoid collaboration Aug 2018 - Dec 2018
- Teaching associate: Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Prof. Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony Aug 2017 - Dec 2017; Jan 2018 - Apr 2018
- Teaching Associate: Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte Jan 2017 – Apr 2017
- Aug 2016 Dec 2016; Aug 2017 Dec 2017 Teaching Associate Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu Aug 2016 - Dec 2016
- Teaching Associate: Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Prof. Chris Baber

Teaching Associate at Mexican Institutions

Aug 2006 – Dec 2013

- Aug 2013 Dec 2013 • Teaching Associate at Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University, Puebla, México.
- Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng at Universidad Madero, Puebla, México. Jan 2012 - Dec 2012
- Jan 2007 Dec 2011 Teaching Associate in Electronic Eng. at Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla, Puebla, México. Aug 2006 - Jun 2007 Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng. at Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco, Puebla, México.

Publications

- 1. T. Bautista, J. Matthew, H. Kerdegari, L. Peralta, and M. Xochicale, "Empirical study of quality image assessment for synthesis of fetal head ultrasound imaging with dcgans," in 26th UK Conference on Medical Image Understanding and Analysis (MIUA '22), arXiv, Jun. 2022, 3-page
- 2. E. Puyol-Antón, B. Ruijsink, B. S. Sidhu, et al., Ai-enabled assessment of cardiac systolic and diastolic function from echocardiography, Mar. 2022. arXiv: 2203.11726 [physics.med-ph; cs.CV; eess.IV], Full Manuscript.
- 3. A. Badillo-Perez, D. Badillo-Perez, D. Coyotzi-Molina, D. Cruz, R. Montenegro, L. Vazquez, and M. Xochicale, "Piloting diversity and inclusion workshops in artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 17th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '22), Mar. 2022.
- 4. R. Beale, J. B. Rosendo, C. Bergeles, et al., "Oxvent: Design and evaluation of a rapidly-manufactured covid-19 ventilator," eBioMedicine, vol. 76, p. 103868, 2022.
- 5. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in human-humanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.
- 6. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and M. Xochicale, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21), Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 7. C. Baker, M. Xochicale, F. Joubert, et al., "Real-time ultrasonic tracking of an intraoperative needle tip with integrated fibre-optic hydrophone," in 2021 IEEE International Ultrasonics Symposium (IUS), 2021, pp. 1-4.

- 8. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in 5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17), Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 9. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17), Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper
- 10. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in 2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics (WeRob '16), Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 11. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.

Posters

- 1. M. Xochicale, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- M. Xochicale, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in human-humanoid interaction," in 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.

Talks

- 1. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in neuromatch 3.0 (NMC3 '20), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation Abstract.
- 2. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.
- 3. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 4. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

Grants, Awards and Honours

- · King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang 🗷 (07/01/2021 - 07/01/2022)
- My M.Sc. student, Alexander Mitton, won the Outstanding Individual Project award 🗹
- King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration (14/04/2020 - 9/06/2020)
- My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, 🗗 🖾 🛗 11/01/2017
- I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh
- 16-18/06/2016
- My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015). 11/2014-11/2018
- I won a Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology.
- Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo. 25-27/05/2013

Skills

Programming Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016-present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LATEX[2006-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016-present], and C++[2015-present], vim[2016-present], with the shell[2010-present], and C++[2015-present], vim[2016-present], with the shell[2010-present], and C++[2015-present], vim[2016-present], with the shell[2010-present], with the present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], and continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present].

Tools GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, BeagleBone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (e.g. Autodesk invetor, blender, FreeCAD)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. PyTorch, and TensorFlow)[2017-present], 3D printing (e.g., flsun, cura) [2019-present], Video framegrabbers (e.g. PCI and usb from ephipan), and Medical imaging (e.g. 3D slicer, ITK-SNAP).

QMS Control documents with standard complience for Good Machine Learning Practice by FDA, Health Canada, and MHRA; IEC 62304 Medical Device Software Standard; BS EN 82304-1:2017 Health Software; IEC 60601-1 Medical electrical equipment; BS EN 61391-2:2010 Ultrasonics;, and BSI 60825-14 Safety of laser products.

Languages Spanish[Native], English[Fluent] and interested in learning Chinese.

Outreach activities and scientific engagement

Organising events on behalf of the Early Career Researcher Network at the BMEIS 01-01-2021 - present. Participation in the Westminster Enterprise Week to engage students aged 14-18 to Biomedical Engineering 10-11-2021

Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students aged 14-18 to STEAM 23-03-2021

Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at BMEIS 02 - 2020 - 06 - 2020

For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist. 20-08-2019

For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI. 09-2019 05-2018

Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: 🛗 and GitHub: 🗂 Research Poster Conference for (2015) (2016) (2016) and (2018) (2018) (3016) (3016) 2016 to 2018

Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: . 2014-2018 Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: , Website: . 2017-2018

Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children (air4children) with the purpose of teaching AIR to children for free. Twitter: ♥@air4children GitHub: 🗖@air4chidlren 2019-Present